[Music]
Heat.
Well, hello, good day, good evening
everybody and welcome back to to the Ask
a Widget Show. Today is episode 293. We
are discussing history, world history
and Indian history and everything in
between and I'm going to take questions
that you all have asked in the comments.
These are questions that I have selected
myself with my own two hands and I'll
take as many of these as possible over
the next couple of hours and let's see
before that let's see who is there on
the live chat. So let's see uh we have
Shou nationalist Vishwendra Singh chat
DSP with a 2-year-old. Fantastic. Good
to have the 2-year-old. Uh Ashima
Mahajan, Ain, Latangi, Suresh,
um Sumit Agarwal, Mystic SK,
Jay Guman, Dnur Singh is here, Wanchada,
Jagish Mali, PK Pro 57,
uh Vamshi, Kalem, Boxer, Commando,
Wanchada, Shrea Sitra from Moscow,
Gagan Badigar, Rayan PK Pro 57, Amea
Tulpig from Germany, Suchin Yadav Boxer
once again Vikash PJ Vnav Nates Chadspir
Solanki
Omikar Pratar Dana Satellite IPK_1S
Gagan Nayan Trianka from Maharashtra
Shuri Namaskar Anuman Mahapatra Oscar
Madison from Houston Texas
uh Kamill Parasar
um who else Abu Singh Aayush Singh,
Nihal Singh, Vikash PJ, Mr. Sakenna.
Um, who else? Dark Knight, Shist,
Ashtavakra, TS Po IC. Okay. Uh, Aus439
from Kik. Is it from Kik or is it from
is it from
Twitch? It's from Twitch. Okay. Karan
Nalawat Rishikesh Dascupta Kamal Parasar
Chaitan Aradya Omar Mani Aditya Singh
Tech Boy
right Priyanka Javalia Chetan Vikash VP
Bruce Wayne Guruda Marath
um who else J25
NIH says pre-recorded hello you think
this is pre-recorded sir pre-recorded
oh man okay Vishal is also here.
Abhishek Nay Gorov Patel boxer.
Okay.
Krishna Raunat from the Surinamese
Netherlands. Okay. Let's get going with
the questions otherwise I will I will
greet you all day and all night. Today
we're going to take questions from the
comments. Not from the live chat, not
from the super chat. So please don't
take super chats. I implore you all. I'm
going to take questions that you all
have asked in the comments. Let's go.
What questions do we have? is the
question that we have to ask ourselves
now. What questions do we have and what
shall we take? Okay. So,
give me a second. All right. Let's go.
Question number one is from Shub. Uh the
the question is about apathide. What was
this policy of apathide? What was the
policy of apathide in South Africa and
how long was it continued and by whom?
So as always I I will not address the
question right away. I'll go into the
background because that's how we
understand what an issue actually is. We
have to understand the the actual
history of the European colonization and
occupation of the southern part of
Africa before we can even start
discussing apathide. Right? So when did
European occupation begin
in southern Africa? This this goes on
this the period of Europe European
occupation of southern Africa. It
started several centuries before apathy
became a thing. There were several
centuries of conquest of occupation of
settlement settler colonization of
conflict of of plundering of resources
and overall over time the construction
of discriminatory systems once the
European rule became u you know
solidified. So the first European
presence
in the southern southern Africa region,
it begins sometime in the middle of the
17th century. It begins with the Dutch.
The Dutch had something called the Dutch
East India Company, right? You may all
have heard of it to some extent. Indians
are mostly uh uh you know aware of the
British East India Company, but well the
Dutch had an East India Company. So the
Dutch East India Company established a
settlement of some kind at the what they
call the Cape of Good Hope which is the
foundation of Cape Town. This is how
Cape Town was founded. The Dutch founded
Cape Town. Um and Dutch settlers started
you know settling in Cape Town and they
eventually expanded. So if you want to
look at the map I mean why not take
let's take a look at the map. So let's
go to the map so that we can discuss it.
um in a little more detail. So we're
talking about South Africa. Okay, this
is South Africa over here. So the Dutch
founded Cape Town in the middle of the
17th century. And eventually after once
their their colony became settled over
there, they started expanding into the
interior parts of what is today South
Africa. Right. Um and you had indigenous
people who obviously lived here who
people who spoke bantu people people who
spoke various other local languages and
the Europeans the Dutch started settling
in these interior parts of South Africa
and displacing the local people the sub
and subjugating the local people that's
how it happens that's how settler
colonization happens so we're talking
about the middle of the 17th century
1650s 1660s7s 80s that sort of thing
then
around in the beginning In the 1800s,
the British took over the Cape Colony
from the Dutch. They defeated the Dutch
and forcibly grabbed the Cape Colony
from the Dutch. Um, and the British. So,
this is in the beginning of the 19th
century. And then the British introduced
their legal system, their their colonial
system uh in the region. The Dutch used
to have slavery. The British said that
they officially abolished slavery. and
they instituted different systems which
were obviously just the same as slavery
but they had different names. So by the
1830s 40s etc the the you know the the
Dutch felt marginalized
and they started moving away from the
British occupied regions and they
established various independent
republics uh what the Transal
uh the orange free state etc. Okay. So
these migrations of the Dutch people, so
the Dutch, the Dutch settlers in South
Africa, they were called the Boers.
Okay, they were called Boers and they
did not like the British because they
wanted to have their own thing. So there
was this conflict that began between the
British who were more powerful and the
Dutch who were the original English
occupiers and subjugators of the region
of South Africa. Uh so so the Dutch went
and settled they created these you know
the the Transval region the orange free
state these uh these uh you know Dutch
ruled areas right and and then what
happened is that in the 19th century in
the 1800s you had the discovery of
diamonds in South Africa and gold
discovery of diamonds and gold which
what does it mean it means tremendous
amounts of Europeans mainly British will
come and settle in South Africa. Yeah.
So this totally transformed the economy
of this region and it brought in a huge
wave of uh immigration mainly from
England from Britain and eventually
there was the competition for resources
and that led to two wars the Anglo boore
wars. Um the second Angloore war there
was a certain sergeant major who was
involved in it as a stretcher bearer as
the leader of the stretcherbearers his
name was Sergeant Major Mandas Gandhi.
Okay. uh Mr. Gandhi was in South Africa
for over 20 years from 18 and he he
returned to India in 1915 and he was
there in the early 1890s so you know
about 20 25 years Mr. Gandhi spend in
South Africa. So you had the two Anglo
boore wars and the British obviously
won. Yeah. They they emerged victorious.
They annexed the Boore republics into
the British empires into the empire and
around 1910 or something the republic
the union of South Africa was formed
which was which united all these
different bore regions and the British
occupied regions and so on into one
single uh dominion dominion status.
Okay. It was it came under the British
Empire and then they instituted new laws
which uh set the white man on a pedestal
and it subjugated the black man. That's
what they did. So the power remained in
the hands of this tiny small white minor
min minority and they created a system
that totally marginalized the black
South Africans in all ways. Politically
marginalized, economically marginalized,
all kinds of discriminatory laws and
acts were passed. Okay. So, uh, South
Africans, the native Africans could
hardly at all own any any land. And, uh,
they were discriminated against,
marginalized in all kinds of ways, that
sort of thing. Um, and they were made to
live separate from the white people.
There were white, you know, beaches that
were allow that were allocated only to
the white people. All the good good
land, good good everything was allocated
to the white people. And eventually
these policies, they they became what we
now call apathide. So then you had
various nationalistic movements uh in
South Africa, African nationalism. You
had something called the national party.
Yeah. All of that. And eventually this
all became officially codified in 1948.
1948. So this was the system of
apathide. This was a policy. It was a
system of institutionalized legalized
racial discrimination, racial
segregation in South Africa. Okay. And
this was implemented by uh the national
party government in 1948 and it lasted
it lasted until around 1994
when FWD clerics government it
officially ended apathide. So you know
apathide laws they determined where
people could live where they could work
where they could go to school where they
could whom they could marry uh and all
kinds of stuff. And uh the white people
were the rulers. They were at the top.
And then you had the non-whites which is
the black people, the the native African
people and also mixed race people and
also Indian origin people. Right. Uh so
that was essentially a path and it it
ended in 1994. Eventually you had the
first free and fair multi-racial
elections in South Africa 1994 which
brought Mr. Dr. Nelson Mandela to power
and the African National Congress became
the dominant political party in South
Africa at this point onwards. So this is
essentially the history of apathide. So
you can't just it's it's not enough to
simply discuss what apathide was. You
have to understand how it happened. You
have to understand the causality.
So it all started in this manner. It's
it's got well a multi-layered
history that goes back to the middle of
the 17th century essentially. Okay. So
that's a pathide. Terrible terrible uh
system obviously brutal.
Now what do we have next? Rinki Chri
says why is Jerusalem a contested place
for Jews, Muslims and Christians? Okay.
Well, okay. Let's discuss this. Let's h
go once again to the map and um where's
the map? Here is the map. And now we
shall move away from Antarctica and
South Africa uh to the uh eastern
Mediterranean region.
So we are obviously discussing uh the
region of Israel today and we have
something called you know so Israel as
you can see it's got all these dashed
lines on the map. You have the Gaza
strip where you have all kinds of um you
know u essentially it's in a state of
war right now. And then we have the West
Bank. The West Bank means the West Bank
of the River Jordan.
And over here there's a city that
straddles these regions which is
Jerusalem. A rather ancient city. And it
like you rightly say it's kind of a
contested space uh contested place for
Jews, for Muslims, for Christians. All
three regard the city as uh as a holy
place for their own religion. So that's
a deal. And so so Jerusalem first of all
where is the okay let's let's go to the
satellite images.
And um so look first of all who are the
first people to to live in in this
region. It was the Jewish people
obviously and uh the Jewish people under
King Solomon around 900 AD or so they
built this big temple, Jewish temple in
Jerusalem. The first temple it's called.
Okay. So it was their city. The Jews
founded the city of Jerusalem and they
had this big temple there called the
first temple. Uh this temple was
destroyed by the Assyrians or the
Babylonians whoever it was. Uh and there
was this period of Jewish exile from
their homeland. And then the Persians
brought the Jews back under uh Emperor
Kurush or Cyrus. And then the Jews built
a second temple in Jerusalem.
And that temple lasted until about 2,000
years ago when the Romans brought it
down. The Romans destroyed it in in
retaliation in response for a Jewish
revolt against the Roman occupation and
rule of the region. So to punish the
Jews, the Romans destroyed that second
temple as well. Today there is one wall
of the second temple. That's all that
remains there. It still stands and it is
called the whailing wall. Let's try and
locate that, shall we? Right. Uh
whailing wall. So let's zoom in. There
we go. So that is the whaling wall.
Uh the western wall of the ancient
temple. This one here. And that's where
that's uh that's essentially the most
sacred uh place of pilgrimage for the
Jewish people. And it's something that
dates back over 2,000 years. And the
second temple was built on the location
if I'm not mistaken of the first temple.
So it's a very sacred place for the
Jewish people. This is the western wall.
And uh it is said I could be look I am
no expert in this but maybe this this uh
so then that so okay we we'll come to
this in a in a in a moment. So that's
why it is sacred for the Jewish people.
There is this wall here. Okay it is the
wall of of the compound of a mosque by
the way over here. We will come to it in
a minute. Now why is it sacred for the
Christian people? Well, it is sacred for
the Christian people because this is the
place where
um Mr. Jesus Christ was uh crucified. So
if we look for Calvary
Calvary, where is that? Um via Dolora
should be Yeah. So this apparently is
the place where Mr. Christ had to walk
with this uh cross on his shoulder. the
via the Lorosa the the painful way and
somewhere here there is this place
called Calvary
let me once again look for it okay
calvary golota golota okay where is it
okay so apparently this is the place
where Mr was crucified there's a rock
over here and uh yeah somewhere over
here and next to it there is the church
of the holy sepulchar which uh could
perhaps
be the resting place of Mr. Christ. I'm
not 100% sure. I'm not very clear about
the Abrahamic religions. If I make some
mistakes, do forgive me. My point is
that the bigger point is valid. This is
where Mr. Christ was apparently
crucified.
And so it's it's not far from the
western wall of the old temple, second
temple, right? As you can see, just a
few hundred meters away. So clearly this
this makes sense that it would be a very
sacred place for the Christian people.
Not just the place where Mr. Christ was
crucified but also the place where he
could which could possibly be his
resting place, final resting place or
the place where he was um he ascended
from whatever it was. Yep. So so that
hopefully explains why this is uh sacred
for the Christians. First we discuss the
Jews then the Christians and then let's
come to the Muslims. So according to
Islamic um uh tradition uh Mr. Muhammad,
the the prophet Muhammad of the uh the
the prophet of Islam, he apparently
visited Jerusalem and the place where he
visited was this is where this uh this
mosque stands today. And perhaps it
could be a disputed place because the
mosque could possibly stand on the place
where the second and first temples also
stood which is why we have the western
wall here which is one of the walls of
the old temple. So that's why there's a
dispute about uh this this uh this dome
of the rock mosque over here. So because
it is closely associated with the
prophet of Islam, prophet Muhammad,
that's why this is a very sacred place
for Muslims as well. So if you look at
the city, the old quarters of Jerusalem,
the old city of Jerusalem, we have
Muslim quarters, we have Jewish quarters
and we have Christian quarters. And that
is the deal about Jerusalem. A sacred
place for three religions and a very
contested place. Everybody
declares that it is holy for them. And
there seems to be some kind of a dispute
between the the Muslims and uh the Jews
about who should have the possession of
the of the site of the ancient temple,
the second temple which is the site of
the first temple.
And for several centuries this this
place was occupied by Muslims you from
more than a thousand years. Uh
we have Sultan Saladin Salahadin who was
the Sultan and who defended Jerusalem
from the crusaders. Uh some of the
crusaders invol included Richard III of
England Richard the Lion Hart Killyong
and so on. And Saladan was able to
defend the city of Jerusalem from the
crusaders. So it's been essentially a
Muslim dominant dominated uh city for a
very long time. So that's the the the
the history of Jerusalem. And that
hopefully explains why it's kind of a
contested space, a place especially
between the Jews and the Muslims. U the
Christians I don't think they claim any
any site that is sacred for the Muslims
and the Jews. Their site is is
different. It's Golka and it is the the
church of the holy sepulkar. That's uh
that is those are the holy places for
Christianity. Those are those are not
claimed by any other religion. But when
it comes to the site of the ancient
temple, well today it looks like there's
a mosque on top of it and it is claimed
by both the religions the Jews as well
as the Muslims and that is the wheel.
Okay. Uh, Swatnil says, "How do the
Spanish flu, which is from 1918 to 1919,
and COVID 19, which is 2019 to present,
how do these two um these two
frightening, terrible, traumatic events,
how do they compare in terms of deaths
and case fatality rate and the age of
victims and the transmissibility,
the illness, severity, uh long-term
effects, virus characteristics, and so
much more. So look, CO is something that
we are familiar with. It's something
that's happened recently. You could say
it's kind of still around. I'm not sure
if anyone still has COVID cases that
that uh anyone's aware of, but it is
what it is. So COVID is is the thing.
And
so the Spanish flu was much worse. It is
something that emerged in the aftermath
of the first world war. The first world
war ends what 1918 or somewhere around
that time. And straight away you have
something called the Spanish flu. Why is
it called the Spanish flu? It is called
the Spanish flu because it was first
discovered by the Americans in Spain.
But it is something that most likely
came from China and it traveled a long
road whichever way you know things you
know pandemics epidemics they travel
they they transmitted through various
vectors.
So when it comes to the Spanish flu,
we're not quite sure how many people
died, but it's definitely between 50 to
100 million. Between 50 to 100 million
people died that is a massive death toll
for the the COVID pandemic. It's about 7
million plus. I mean that's the official
death toll. We don't know for sure
exactly if there there have been more
deaths or not, but the official death
toll is around 7 million.
And that's uh from 2019 all the way
until today. Spanish flu it was just a
couple of years in 199 198 and 1919. And
in those two years it killed between 50
to 100 million people. It infected more
than 500 million people about a third of
the entire world's population at the
time. Right? And the CFR case fatality
rate was in excess of 2.5%. For COVID
it's around 1%.
And here's where even if you would
disregard the case fatality rate and how
many people were infected and how many
people died, here's where the two
pandemics were very different because
for the Spanish flu, the people who were
affected the most were people who who
were between 25 to 40 years in age.
Young people, they were the ones who
were affected the most. Between 25 and
40 years of age. If you were younger
than 25, you were less likely to die as
a as a result of the Spanish flu. If you
were above 40 years of age, you were
less likely to die because of it. But
between 25 to 40 is where you had the
most fatalities. Weird, isn't it?
Strange. For COVID,
the people who are who died the most,
the you know, that's the people who are
65 and above. So, it's older people who
were affected more by COVID and people
with uh comorbidities, pre-existing
comorbidities. If someone has diabetes,
if someone already had cancer, if
someone had some other illness or
disease and then they got COVID, then
they were more likely to die of COVID.
But regular healthy people were less
likely to die of COVID. So that's that's
the kind of thing and obviously you
would have uh you know, so the COVID
virus is a SARS COV2 corona virus and
the Spanish flu virus was an H1N1
influenza virus. So pretty different
viruses. Um and they both had their own
complications and people died of various
uh causes like multi-organ failure and
whatever else in the case so in the case
of the Spanish flu you had people who
died of multi-organ failure lots of that
happened in the case of case of SARS
corona virus you have people who die who
are dying of immune over reaction
cytoine storms so totally different
mechanisms and also people would know
that's the vaccine right people who died
of blood clots and all that's the
vaccine thing that's the vaccine
injury thing. So the vaccine perhaps may
have may have killed more people than
the virus itself.
I remember, you know, I've been doing
the Ask a Bij show since when? 2021. In
21, 22, even 23, if I spoke about the
Corona virus on one of my live streams,
you would have this big YouTube
disclaimer afterwards below the live
stream,
you know, and even on Spotify, those
episodes would have big COVID
disclaimers that here is the official
thing about Corona virus. Don't listen
to what anybody says. only listen to the
the official science vaccines are good
blah blah I know vaccines are good but
the western fiser vaccine and all
they've killed people they've killed
more people than the save saved it and
there's also the possibility that this
virus may have been human engineered
right if you spoke about this 3 years
ago they would essentially cancel you
they would uh delete all your social
media accounts and and so on you could
not speak about that But it's possible
that maybe this virus was human
engineered. So yeah, that's the
difference between the COVID virus and
the uh and the Spanish flu virus and the
epidemic overall.
Amisha says, "If Hitler wanted to create
a Third Reich, what were the first and
second Reichkes?" That's a great
question. Why doesn't anyone ask these
questions? Very, very, sounds very
simple. We had the Third Reich, Hitler
Reich, Nazi Germany. What was the first
Reich and the second Reich?
Great question.
So the first Reich was the what is
called the Holy Roman Empire which
lasted about a thousand years and then
you had the the German Empire which
starts in 1871. So the Holy the
so-called Holy Roman Empire. It begins
in the year I think 800 AD when Carolus
Magnus the king of the Franks Shagleman
was appointed the the first emperor of
the Holy Roman Empire by the whoever was
the pope at the time. You can look it up
if you are interested in in knowing the
name of that of that pope. So
Charlemagne became the first emperor of
what was then later to be known the Holy
Roman Empire. And
and then you had someone called Otto I
who was the first German properly
Germanic Germanspeaking uh king of this
or or or so-called emperor of this Holy
Roman Empire, Otto I or Otto the Great.
And throughout history, this Holy Roman
Empire, it uh it was located in mainly
German speakaking territories, which is
why it was mostly a Germanic empire,
right? So the word Reich R E I C H
Reich, it has the same root
as the word Raja in Sanskrit. Raja and
Reich is the same thing. The third Reich
means the third Raja. So the first Raja
was the so-called Holy Roman Empire and
you had you know the the founder you
could say is Carlos Magnus or Shalimman
and you had Otto the first then you had
Frederick the first Barbar Roa the the
red red bearded fellow then you had the
last emperor was Francis or something
and so it lasted from 800 AD to 1800 in
the early 1800s it was it came to an end
because of the Napoleonic wars Napoleon
put an end to the so-called Holy Roman
Roman Empire. So Napoleon ended it. Then
you have the second Reich which is the
German Empire which begins in 1871.
Right? So there was something called the
FrancoRussian War which happened in the
1860s and 1870s
and the Prussians. So there was no
Germany until 1871 by the way. Okay,
here's the deal. And by the way, there
was no Germany until 1871. You had all
these people who spoke Germanic
languages
and the territory is today what we call
well Germanic lands Germany magna that's
what the Romans called it but it was
never one country or one kingdom it was
a whole bunch of hundreds of different
principalities and dukes and whatnot it
was unified for the first time ever in
uh by by the iron chancellor Otoon
Bismar and Uh it was the unification
happened under the emperor Kaiser
William the Wilhelm the first Kaiser
Wilhelm the first the f the first ever
unification proper unification of all
the Germanic states of all the German
states 1871. So uh the mastermind behind
the unification was Ottoon Bismar the
iron chancellor of Germany. Um and uh he
established a very conservative
empire a pretty militaristic empire and
a very modern empire with a very modern
education system and very modern
administration.
And then you had the second emperor
Kaiser Wilhelm II who was the last was
the last. Yeah. He abdicated wasn't he?
He he abdicated at the end of the second
world war and that was the end of the
German empire the second Reich
and then you have the beginning of the
third Reich which uh was the brainchild
of uh of the Austrian painter. Okay. So
three different periods of time 800 AD
to 1800 AD then 1871 all the way to 1918
and then 1930 is 35 onwards to 45
roughly 10 years the so the first one is
a thousand years the second one is what
30 40 less than 50 years and the third
one is about a decade
okay
feminist slayer says what no was the
Trail of peers 1830s an unavoidable
result of US expansion or a deliberate
policy of ethnic cleansing. A really
interesting question. Let's go to the
map where we oh here is map. We go to
the United States.
So in the 1800s
you you had the you know the relentless
westward expansion of the Europeans
European occupiers the settler
colonizations of the Americas.
Um and this is the period before the the
the the the civil war. So you have
slavery in the US.
The United States at the time was much
smaller than what it is today. By the
way this was not the map of the US at
the time. it was simply uh you know
mostly concentrated in the south in in
the south and the east.
So
there used to be these uh people you
know the native Americans who lived in
the southeastern United States. Uh you
had various uh native American ethnic
groups like the Churroi, the Seino, the
Chasaw, the Choto, the Muscogee or Creek
and so on who all their ancestral lands
were in the southoutheast of what is
currently the United States and these
people they were forcibly relocated
about I don't know the official figures
are about 60,000 to 100,000 or something
like that so they were forcibly
relocated from their ancestral homelands
to territories west of the Mississippi
River so
if you want to know where the
Mississippi River is have to go to
Galveston Island over
Kaba Devaka. Kabad Devaka. That's a
whole different story. So you have the
Mississippi River here. Okay. This This
is the San Hasinto River. Where is the
bigger one? Where's the Where's the
Mississippi?
Where is Mississippi River? Yes. Where
is it? Let's try and locate.
Uh,
okay. We need to zoom out a little.
Let's just because we know that. Okay. I
I know where it starts.
Um,
for example, if you go to Minneapolis
all the way to the north in the US, just
zoom in. We have the Mississippi River
here and then then it goes on and on and
on and on and on. Goes all the way
south.
Let's just do this exercise, shall we?
This here is the Mississippi. It
eventually merges with the with the
Missouri River, and that's the longest
the largest water system in the world.
Obviously, this here is the Mississippi.
So, I'm actually tracing the path of the
river all the way down south.
And here we have Newuel Orleon, New
Orleans.
Yeah. Yeah. So, I shouldn't have been at
Galveston Island. It should have been
New Orleans. Okay. So, the Native
Americans were forcibly relo relocated
west of the Mississippi River in totally
different territories which they were
not, you know, which which were not
their original homelands.
So this resulted in the deaths of I
don't know thousands, tens of thousands,
we don't know how many people. Um and it
was horrible. So it it was called the
trail of tears. And this was obviously
all legal, right? Because uh President
uh Andrew Jackson passed he signed a law
called the Indian Removal Act or
something. So it was all done legally.
Okay, there's nothing illegal about
this. Totally legal. So these people
were all moved forcibly to you know
these barren regions of the US where you
have desert and stuff and why was this
done is the question. So you can see
it's it's all barren pueblo and so on.
So why was this done? There's a good
reason for this because you know, you
know, uh all these fertile lands,
Virginia, etc., Tennessee, uh Georgia,
Indiana, Mississippi, Missouri, all of
these lands, well, they were very
fertile. There was a tremendous uh
amount of extremely fertile agricultural
land here. So you could do all kinds of
different kinds of farming, cotton
farming for example, cotton cultivation,
other kinds of cultivation, gold mining
and settlement, European settlement in
the region. If you have native people
living there, then there's going to be
trouble. So get rid of the natives. So
that's what it was, right? So this was
all done legally according to the laws
of the Europeans who had settled in the
in the United States in in North
America. And this uh and how was this
done? It's not like you pass a law and
you tell them to leave. You have to
force them to leave. So this policy,
this act was implemented through
military force. Okay? Through military
force. And this led to the deaths of I
don't know tens of thousands of people
possibly. I'm sure the official figures
are they underrepresent what actually
happened. But that is what it is.
Was this an unavoidable result of US
expansion? There was nothing unavoidable
about it. It was perfectly 100%
avoidable.
But the Americans, the Europeans did not
want to live anywhere close to the
natives. So they just said, "Get rid of
the natives. Just displace them thousand
miles away." That sort of thing. So it
was a deliberate policy of ethnic
cleansing. Definitely 100% nobody can
deny this. It was a deliberate policy of
ethnic cleansing. Did it lead to
genocide? Well, it depends on what you
mean by genocide. What's your definition
of genocide? 10,000 20,000 people die.
Is it genocide or do do you need people
to die in the hundreds of thousands or
or millions? I'm not sure. So, I'm not
sure if it fits whatever is the
definition of genocide as per I don't
know UN or whatever. I'm not sure about
that. But it was definitely ethnic
cleansing and obviously genocide has
obviously happened. The the formation of
the US, you know, well,
behind it is is genocide. So you have
this nation the United States is
artificial nation which it's been
created it's it's built on the found on
three foundations one is slavery the
second is ethnic cleansing and third is
genocide the fourth is obviously theft
of land uh that's these are facts I mean
I'm not trying to throw any shade at the
people who live in the US today the
descendants of those who did all this
it's not their fault but the US is
obviously native land it's not the land
that actually belongs to the it now
belongs to them because they occupy it.
If occupation is law, well, there you
have it. Then it's the rule of the
jungle. It's no longer civilized, you
know, rules, but it is what it is. Okay.
A feminist slayer says, how critical was
Gettysburg 1863 in deciding the outcome
of the American Civil War? So, the
American Civil War, it starts in what?
1861.
I think it's 1861 and it ends in 1865
and uh one of the well triggers of this
was the election of Abraham Lincoln to
the presidency of the United States in
1860 1860 right so uh so you have this
terrible civil war that happens why does
the civil war happen first of all it's
because you have this clash of
lifestyles clash of economic lifestyles
and so on the southern states They
wanted to continue the practice of
slavery,
right? And that gave them tremendous
economic benefits. In the north, they
had they had new technology like what
the cotton gin or whatever it's called,
which could do the work of I don't know
10 slaves, 100 slaves uh in the time it
took for one slave to do whatever
something. So, you know, they no longer
needed slavery. So, it was no longer
economically necessary to have slaves in
the north. But in the south they wanted
to continue the tradition. They had not
been yet been exposed to this
technology. So the south said we want
slavery. We want to continue it. The
north said we have to abolish slavery.
And that's why the two sides went to
war. They did not simply go to war. The
southern states seceded from the US.
They said that we are they essentially
de facto partitioned the nation. Right?
They said that we are creating our own
separate nation
and that's why there was a civil war in
the US. So uh this battle of Gettysburg
like you say happened in 1863 and it was
a decisive pivotal critical turning
point in this civil war which began in
1861. The civil war is a is a whole huge
chapter of American history. So you have
two sides in the civil war. The union
and the confederates. The union means
the north. The confederates means the
south. So Gettysburg was a decisive
pivotal moment. It's a turning point in
this in this war. It resulted in a major
northern victory, Union victory. And
what did this victory do? The South, the
Confederate forces, they had this this
this great general called Robert E. Lee,
and he was in the process of conducting
his second invasion of the North at this
time. and the disaster, the defeat of
the of the Confederate forces in
Gettysburg, it halted Robert El's second
invasion of the north. And this was this
marked the beginning of the decline of
the u of the fortunes of the south, the
Confederate military fortunes. And this
obviously had a critical impact on the
war's final outcome, which was a victory
of the north.
So why was this decisive? First of all,
this was the bloodiest battle of the
entire civil war. It is said that there
are more than 50,000 people who died in
this total cumulatively north plus south
casualties combined. More than 50,000
people died. 50,000 soldiers died. So
Robert Elie wanted to he wanted to
relieve pressure from war on Virginia.
So you know if you go to the map once
again uh Virginia is a territory one of
the first territories ever to be
established you know in so this is
Virginia it is named after Queen
Elizabeth
um and I've discussed that in in other
videos so Robert Lee wanted to
essentially uh march into Virginia okay
and uh and he wanted to relieve pressure
essentially on on on Virginia and he
wanted to gather supplies from the north
and that sort of thing. So the defeat in
in Gettysburg it forced the south the
confederate forces to retreat and uh
this was the beginning of the decline.
So before this they had enjoyed multiple
victories the confederate forces and
this victory ended the momentum of
Robert E. Le's military campaign. It uh
had a critical morale crashing uh you
know effect on the Confederate forces.
It gave uh Lincoln's leadership you know
momentum public confidence. The public
was now confident that Lincoln will be
able to get things done. And it also
also showed that the northern forces
could decisively repel Robert E. Lee who
was looked at looked upon as a superman
kind of person at the time. you know the
the war's most talented commander that
sort of thing and after that the the
southern forces became defensive until
that that time they were trying to march
to the north and invade the north after
the defeat in Gettysburg they became
defensive defensive defensive and
eventually you you you had other other
uh battles that were happening at the
same time Vixsburg is an example uh that
also was was lost by the confederates so
this eventually you know had a
cumulative effect of uh of eventually
leading to the to the defeat of the
Confederate forces. So that's that is
it. So it had massive uh psychological
effects. It it destroyed the morale of
the confederates. It had it caused
massive casualties and eventually its
strategic consequences were such that
the south was eventually defeated.
Okay. Anul says, "I've got to know that
in 1953, Prime Minister Mr. Neu seeded
an 11,000 square kilometer valley called
the Cabo Valley in Manipur to Myanmar
without asking the people of Manipur
whether they were okay with this." Okay.
And currently most of the various
insurgent groups in the of Northeast
India operate from this valley. We'll
not sure about that but okay. Uh so what
are the details about this value that
and why did Mr. Nehu seed it to Burma?
Uh and what benefits could India have
got if this value was never seeded by by
Mr. Neu to Burma? Okay. Uh so look a
long history behind this.
Manipur has been a was an independent
kingdom for more than 2,000 years. Maybe
more than 3,500 years. Long story. We'll
not go into that. Now in the around 1800
1799 to 1800 or somewhere some somewhere
around that this time Manipur came under
the occupation of Burma. Burma was a big
kingdom at the time. It was called the
AA the kingdom of Ava. So the kingdom of
AA occupied Manipur because Manipur was
busy fighting itself you know with the
various princes were fighting each other
for the kingdom of Manipur. And what
happened is that the neighbor comes and
takes over. So Manipur was occupied by
Burma for seven years. the seven years
of devastation is what it's called. Uh
and eventually Manipur regained its well
independence so to say with British help
which means that you're not really
sovereign. You become a vasal. Um and
then there was a war between the Brit
the Burmese and the and the English the
Anglo Burmese war the first Anglo
Burmese war which ended in 1826.
Uh so when the Burmese had taken over
Manipur obviously they took over Kabo
Valley clearly obviously right because
it was part of Manipur. Um
after the defeat of the Burmese in 1826
there was a treaty that was signed. It
was it is called the treaty of Yandabo.
And in this treaty of Yandabo the
British gave they transferred control of
the of the Kabo Valley to the Burmese.
And the the deal the treaty was that the
Burmese would would pay compensation
yearly compensation
to the Maharaja of Manipur. I don't know
how many rupees per year or whatever but
it was silver rupees sika rupees or
something it's called.
So from 1826 onwards the Burmese
were given control by the British of the
Kabo valley but it was not Burmese
territory it was Manipuri territory and
as as and they paid a rent a yearly rent
to Manipur. So you don't pay rent to
somebody if that's your territory right
let's say you go and live in someone's
let's say you are renting an apartment
you're going to pay rent to the actual
owner of the apartment. If you are the
owner, you have no need to pay rent. So
the Burmese similarly were paying rent
for the Kabo Valley to the king of
Manipur. Which clearly means that the
Burmese were not the actual owners of
the Kabo Valley. The Manipur kingdom,
the kingdom of Manipur, the Raja of
Manipur, Maharaj of Manipur was the
actual owner. But the British created
this this complication. They said,
"Okay, the Burmese can have it. They can
control it provided that they give rent.
They pay rent. Otherwise, it's not
yours. otherwise they can't have it. So
there was a deal. So the Burmese were
using it because it's very rich in
resources and whatnot. You know it's
full of forests, teak wood and whatnot.
So it's it's very rich in resources and
the Burmese
wanted those possibly those resources
and that's why they were willing to pay
a substantial amount of rent so to say
to the king of Manipur. Now Manipur
becomes a part of India in 1949
and apparently for a couple more years
or whatever the the Burmese paid the
rent and then they stopped paying rent
and that was it and Mr. Dehu did not
look out for the interests of the now
that Manipur is part of the union of
India then the Kabo Valley becomes part
of the interests of the nation of India.
It is still Indian territory. If it was
Manipur territory and Manipur became
part of India, then then the Kabo Valley
should be Indian territory.
But the Burmese stopped paying rent and
the Mr. Nu just let it go just like
that. This territory became Burmese.
Okay, that's the deal.
This territory was always Manipuri
territory.
And yeah, Mr. Nu was a very generous
person. generous to others not to us to
foreigners he also okay I'll not go into
the list of the laundry list of all the
stuff that he's done but that that is a
deal okay so that's the history why did
Mr. Nu did do something why did he seed
it to Burma listen I have no idea why
Mr. did what he did. He did lots of
magnificent things. Why did he do do
those magnificent things? I am not a
mind reader. I have no idea why he did
these things. I know what he did. I know
what what were the consequences of that.
I can tell you the things that Shin
Neuji has done. And I can tell you what
have been the consequences of those
actions taken by Shin Neuji. I cannot
tell you why he did what he did. That
only he can tell us. But he is no longer
with us which is uh tremendously
distressing that uh that he is not with
us today. See very sad for us but yeah
so so that's why we will never know why
Mr. Neu did these things. Yeah. Uh yeah
so it is a value that's rich in
resources and so on.
Okay no says what is the history of
northern Africa in the pre-Abrahamic
era?
What language families did this did
their languages belong to? What
religions did they follow? Which
ethnicities did they belong to? And what
did they look like? The people of north
northern Africa in the pre-Abrahamic
era. So what's the Abrahamic era? Let's
say it's around 1000 AD 1000 BC BC
BC. Um roughly speaking, we don't know
exactly if Mr. Abraham existed. Probably
he did, but we don't know when he exist
existed and so on. So let's say it's
around 10,000 BC. So that's the
beginning of the Abrahamic era.
Um now so what was the history of
Northern Africa before that? So first of
all let's take a look at North Africa
what it looks like. Since we are
discussing a region we can always refer
to the map. So we are referring to this
this part of Africa. Okay. As you can
see this this part of Africa that's all
green. Then you have this
rather arid part of Africa which is
Namibia, South Africa and then you have
the Sahara desert and the regions north
of that. So
so this is essentially northern Africa
over here which is the part of Africa
that touches essentially the
Mediterranean Sea and the eastern
Atlantic Ocean.
So it starts from Egypt. It has
presently Libya, Tunisia, Algeria,
Morocco
and that's about it. Probably not
Western Sahara. So that's that's what we
mean first of all by North Africa. Now
what's the history of North Africa?
Well, the history of North Africa is
obviously the human history of North
Africa that we're talking about. So if
you want to talk, okay, let's go to
satellite images. Let's go to Morocco.
And somewhere in Morocco, let us say
Jibel,
Jibel
Hood,
probably not here. It's some other part
of Morocco, somewhere else. But it's in
Morocco in a place called Jabel Hud that
you find the oldest archaeological
evidence of homo sapiens. That goes back
about 300 or 4,000 4 three or 400,000
years before today. Roughly 400,000
years. So that's the oldest evidence
that we have of Homo sapiens.
Uh so that's the beginning so you could
say of the history of northern Africa
with the history of homo sapiens there.
Now
there is something called the the desert
over here the Sahara desert. Right? So
the Sahara desert became a thing about
4,000 years around 4,000 BC. Before
4,000 BC this place was all green green
green. You had forests and rivers and
whatnot. But because of climate change
which has always been a thing uh this
place became all deserted. Now what
kingdoms did we have in northern Africa
before the Abrahamic era? Obviously you
had Egypt. Egypt is the second oldest
civilization that we know of in the
world, right? It its root go its roots
go back almost 4,000 almost 5,000 BC
possibly. So Egypt the second oldest
civilization that we are aware of then.
So that so that is kind of the oldest uh
civilized uh history that we know of of
northern Africa. So you have the uh
Egyptian people obviously who lived
here. Um
excuse me. So
language families you had the
Afroasiatic language family of which
Egyptian is a very big uh language. Then
you have what the Nyloic peoples.
uh you had the the Nubian people who
also were a major uh ethnic group. They
are the ancestors of today's Sudanese
people mostly. Then you had the people
who the Amaz
called them the Berbers which is not a
nice thing to say about someone but they
called them the Berbers or barbarians.
So you have the Burbar people who lived
all across northern Africa uh Libya,
Algeria, Tunisia, Morocco
uh and they their language family was
also part of the Afroasiatic language
family and they eventually uh you know
set up the big uh uh city of Carthage,
the kingdom of Carthage and they fought
Rome and all that stuff
and eventually it was all occupied by
Rome this region. So that's kind of the
history of Northern Africa. You have
Egypt and then you have the the the
Berber peoples. So the major language
family is the Afroasiatic language
family. Um religions Egypt obviously had
its own polytheistic religion. Very uh
rich, very complex polytheistic culture.
Uh so that's the religion of Egypt. uh
the Berbar people also had polytheism
and they had animism, ancestor worship
and so on. Then you had the Phoenicians
who also made their way into the region
from the eastern shores of the
Mediterranean which is the Lebanon
region. And the Phoenicians also they're
the ones who set up Carthage
uh the kingdom of Carthage and so on. Uh
so once again this was a polytheistic
set of religions that we had. What do
they look like? They kind of look like
the people who live there today.
Yeah. Yeah, they would have they would
have looked pretty similar to the people
who live in the region today.
Right. Okay. Next.
Shub says, "How powerful was the USSR in
terms of of its military capabilities as
compared to the US at different points
of time during the cold war?" So, the
cold war begins roughly 1945 as soon as
the Second World War ends or you could
say 1950 if you want, whatever you want.
I I see it beginning at in 1945. And it
ended in let's say 1990 or 91. So 1945
to 1990 that's about what 45 years. The
cold war lasted about 45 years. So how
powerful was the USSR compared to the US
in terms of military strength at the
time. So it all begins. So the military
comparison also has mult different uh
subcomparisons.
How powerful
were the armed were the air forces of
each nation? How powerful were the
navies of each nation? How powerful were
the submarine forces of each nation? How
powerful were the ballistic missile
capabilities of each nation? And how
powerful were the respective nuclear
strengths? You look at all of this and
and then how powerful were they
continentally in Europe and elsewhere
and so on. So it's it's pretty complex
comparison that we're talking about
here. So first of all the Americans are
the ones who first uh they first created
the atomic bomb right so initially they
have this big advantage over the USSR
they were the only nation in the world
with a nuclear weapons technology
weapons of mass destruction then the
USSR quickly caught up with the US they
also tested their atomic bombs then both
nations had nuclear weapons capabilities
but the Americans had a huge head start
over the Russians or the Soviets. And uh
by the 1960s, the Americans had I don't
know maybe 25,000 nuclear warheads and
the the Soviets had maybe 500, maybe a
thousand, maybe 3,000, I'm not sure,
something like that. Huge. There was a
huge gap between the two nations. The
Americans had way better ballistic
missiles than the Russians once again
than the Soviets. But by the 60s7s
eventually you have parity that happens
between the two nations in terms of
nuclear weapons capabilities and
ballistic missile capabilities. The
Americans uh they the Russians probably
had better long range strategic bombers
than the Americans for a significant
period of time during the cold war. The
Americans dominated the oceans. They had
way better power projection
capabilities. they
were able to cut off the USSR to a
significant extent from um the Atlantic
and and and Pacific oceans. Obviously,
the USSR did have its uh Vladivosto
facilities and the Atlantic capabilities
and so on, but not the way the Americans
had. The Americans had the freedom of
the oceans. The Soviets had to kind of
squeeze through choke points to get into
the big oceans, that sort of thing. So,
that that gave the Americans a huge
advantage. the Americans um the Soviets
had a huge massive conventional
advantage in Europe. They had this
massive massive ground army, millions of
millions of enlisted soldiers. And uh
NATO estimated that the Soviets could
overrun the whole of Europe in a few
weeks or months. That's how powerful
they were. Um so naval power, the
Americans were better submarines. I
think the Soviets also had great
submarines, very powerful submarines,
uh, nuclear submarines obviously and
both nations had these this nuclear
triad, air, land and sea submarine based
uh, ballistic missile based and and uh,
you know, different three different ways
of delivering nuclear weapons including
a robust second strike capability. The
Americans were always ahead of the
Soviets technologically
in in the in uh in the field of
computing. For example, the Americans
always were ahead of of the Soviets in
space. The Soviets were way ahead of the
US for a for a very long time until 1969
or something when the Americans, you
know, leaprogged the the Soviets and so
on. uh and eventually by the 19 late
1970s and and the in the in the 1980s
the Soviets start you know their
standards start declining and so on and
then you have Gorbachov who essentially
you know puts an end to the USSR so
essentially that's how it went
says who were these Yamna invaders what
new evidence do we have of these people
I don't know about new evidence but I
can tell you who the Yamna
um Yamaya. So the Yamaha people were
look if you look at the history of
Europe, the the old history of Europe,
not not the past 1,000 2,000 years, the
actual deeper history of Europe around
5,000 6,000 BC. Then you will see that
the people of Europe look very different
from what they look today.
You had people with much darker skin in
Europe than the Europeans that we have
today.
Um,
for example, we know of Stonehenge. Do
we do you know what Stonehenge is? U, if
you don't, we can Google it very
quickly. I'm sure you will recognize
what it looks like. So, let's go to
Google and we will Stonehenge
historical landmark. So you see this
monument right very famous monument it's
a bunch of stones that are standing
together and it marked the various
solstesses and astronomical events that
people observed back in the day now no
now nobody cares about that but that's
how it was so the people who built
Stonehenge
are they really the ancestors of today's
English and British people not quite to
some extent today's
English or British people
they have the matrinal lineages that
come from the Stonehenge era but not the
patrineal lineages. The patrinal
lineages come from the east.
So what exactly happened is the
question. See about foreign about
roughly 5,000 years before today there
was this massive invasion
of Europe from the east. It is said that
it came from the Pontic Caspian step
which is Eastern Europe and Central
Asia.
So a bunch of horse riding barbarians
just rampaged across Europe coming from
the east
and they conducted
a large scale genocide in Europe. They
killed off all the men or most of the
men wherever they settled
and they
then inter married or whatever you want
to call it with the local women
and the people of Europe are the
descendants of those unions.
Um
so that's the deal. So the Yamna
invaders were this bunch of invaders who
came from the east and invaded Europe
and completely changed the genetics and
demographics of Europe.
The there were tremendous uh conquerors
uh they were uh horse riding people and
they were far more militaristically
aggressive etc than the people of Europe
who were kind of settled right. So uh
that is who the Yamna were. Now you know
it is it is said that uh the these are
the original Aryan invaders of India.
Well that's uh that's a whole different
story. We'll not go into that. So it's
not it's not true. Uh so that's who the
Yamna invaders were. What language did
they speak? It is believed that they
spoke some kind of Indo-Uropean
language,
possibly one of the ancestral languages
that gave rise to multiple modern
European languages.
But they most likely, it is believed,
spoke an Indo-Uropean language. Do we
have evidence that they spoke an
Indo-Uropean language? We have zero
evidence for that. It is believed
by a lot of scholars that they spoke an
Indo-Uropean language. We don't have any
actual evidence of it.
It is also believed that they practiced
the old Indo-Uropean religion which is
well as far as we know the Vic religion
but the Vic religion or it kind of
frowns upon genocide doesn't it? So
anyway it is said that it is believed
once again that they practiced some form
of the old Indo-Uropean religion. Do we
have evidence of that? We don't have
evidence of that. What evidence do we
have from the archaeological record? We
have evidence that these people they
practiced burials. They did not do
cremations. They practiced burials for
whatever reason. Maybe wood was not
plentiful in the step region. Uh but
they practiced burials. Um it was a
militaristic society based on the
archaeological evidence that we have. It
was a patriarchal society based on the
archaeological evidence that we have.
Maybe it was an oligarchic society. A
high status individuals were buried with
weapons and objects that that tell you
that this this person is high status.
And they were buried with red pigment on
them, red ochre pigment. And then mounds
were constructed on top of the burials,
the the kuran kind of mounds, that sort
of thing. But they were buried in pits.
The word for pit in Russian is Yamna.
And that's why these people are called
the Yamna people. It's from a Russian
word. We have no idea what they actually
called it themselves,
right? The people of France, they called
themselves the Fay, the French people.
The people of Germany, they call call
themselves the Deutsche people, the
Germans. The people of India, we call
ourselves Bharata. What did the these
people call themselves? They certainly
did not call themselves Yamna. We have
no idea what they called themselves. So
essentially, this is what we know about
the Yamaya people. Now, what other
question do we have? Uh, AJ Ra says,
"You mentioned a Yamna invasion of
Europe.
So, how were the original Europeans
like? What did they look like? Were they
similar in looks and genes to current
day Middle Eastern and African people?
Does it mean that the painter was wrong
when he claims that he was from a pure
Aryan race?
Okay. So, who are the original
Europeans? I I said right that the
original Europeans did not look like
today's Europeans. They were they had
darker skin and so on. So
So we know that the Yamna invasion
happens roughly 5,000 years before today
about 5,000 years before today. Before
that you had essentially two different
uh genetic or ethnic groups in Europe.
Um that's what genetic analysis tells
us. Okay. One is called the western
hunter gatherers and the second is the
early European farmers. So the western
hunter gatherers are are an older
population. They were an older
population in Europe and the early
European farmers they themselves had
migrated from somewhere in the east
maybe Anatolia
maybe east of Anatolia we're not quite
sure but you know you don't go eastwards
of of Anatolia you never say that. So,
so the early European farmers they had
migrated from let's say Anatolia and uh
they also had some other older ancestry
obviously obviously everyone has older
ancestry. So these two groups they
dominated the genetic makeup of Europe
before the arrival of the Yamna invaders
and the complete genocide that they
perpetrated the western hunter gatherers
and the early European farmers. So
what did these people look like? Uh they
were different looking from the Yamna.
They were smaller than the Yamna. First
of all, the Yamna were big guys. 5 10 6
feet. What did the Yamna look like?
First of all, the Yamna guys were about
5 10 6 feet tall. They had strong bones,
uh strong skulls. Uh they were muscular.
Their diet was mainly milk and meat.
They were horse riders. The Yamna had
dark hair and they had light brown skin,
not white skin.
So that's what the Yamna looked like.
Now
we know from ancient DNA that what the
uh the pre-amnia Europeans would have
looked like. So the western hunter
gatherers, they had a weird mix of
characteristics. They had dark skin.
What kind of dark skin?
How do I put it across delicately?
Think of the Bangladesh cricket team or
the Sri Lankan cricket team. That sort
of dark skin. Okay. Uh, so the western
hunter gatherers had reasonably dark
skin but they had blue eyes or green
eyes and they had dark hair. So imagine
imagine if the Sri Lankan cricket team
had blue eyes.
That's what the western hunter gatherers
would look like. Okay. So I mean that's
what DNA analysis tells us that blue
eyes may have been common most likely uh
among these people
but they had dark skin. Now you also
have the early European farmers that we
mentioned and these folks they had
lighter skin compared to the western
hunter gatherers uh but it was
definitely darker than the skin that we
have that the modern Europeans have
today. And these early European farmers
who came from Anatolia or maybe further
east, they had brown hair, brown eyes
and dark hair
and uh they did not have light light
eyes or light hair. So they had brown
skin, maybe light brown skin. They had
brown eyes, brown eyes and and dark
hair. So that's what they look like. So
these are the traits that you had in
Europe. You know, that's what the
Europeans look like before the Yamna
arrived. The Western hunter gatherers
were more primitive. Apparently they
lived in small groups, tribal groups,
small groups, 50 people, 100 people
maximum. They were hunters and they were
fishers. So their lifestyle was hunter
gather lifestyle, hunting, fishing,
gathering. They used stone tools and
they left behind cave art with bisons
and whatnot. And they had various kinds
of burial sites and they had no
agriculture.
And they I think they had domesticated
dogs but no other domestic animals. The
early European farmers they once again
like they came from Anatolia and from
Anatolia apparently they brought
agriculture and they brought animal
husbandry
which animals definitely not the bulls
right not the Indian cows um and so they
had they were more evolved apparently
than the western hunter gatherers they
had organized villages they had
cultivation of crops and they had
domestic animals and so on. So that's
what the early uh pre-amna Europeans
looked like uh what their lifestyles
were and uh how much of them survive.
There are some people maybe in Spain and
the Basque region who still have more of
the old European genetics and people
from Northern Europe they have almost no
uh original European genetics. They're
purely Yamna. So how did the northern
Europeans develop blonde hair and blue
eyes when the Yamna themselves did not
have it? Well, that genetic mutation
happened sometime later and somehow it
was highly preferred. So natural
selection.
Okay.
Amisha says what happened in the battle
of Adaspis?
Why was King Porus assassinated? Why is
King Porus mentioned in Greek records
but not in Indian records?
So there used to be this river which
still exists. We called it, our
ancestors called it the Vitashta,
Vitashta river.
Today it's called the Gilim, the Gilim
River. The Greeks they called it the
Hidaspis.
I have no idea what Hyaspis means, but
they called it the Hidaspis. And that's
why it's called the battle of Hidaspis.
If you go to if you go to Wikipedia,
it's going to say battle of Bahai's
peace.
See, battle of Haida's peace.
It doesn't say the battle of Jelum or
whatever it will say. Okay, it's also
known as something battle of Jalum or
whatever, first battle of Jalum. But the
primary name they will use is the battle
of the Haidaspiece.
Does anyone call that river the
Haidaspiece? But still they will use a
fake foreign name for the for the river.
Anyhow, what was this battle? So, we
know that uh Alexander the Greek
attempted an invasion of India um in
what 327 BC until 324 or 323 BC
somewhere around that time. Right? So
Alexander attempts this invasion of
India and the biggest battle in this
invasion happens
on the banks of the Vitashta river which
is the battle of the H highas piece as
as that's what the Greeks called it. So
the battle is between Alexander and a
local local village chief. Okay. Uh who
was who who the Greeks called Porus.
They they depicted him as this great
magnificent Indian king.
Um so they call him Porus. We don't know
what his real name was. Was it Porova?
Was it Purusham? We have no idea. The
Greeks called him Porus. And apparently
Alexander had had instructed Porus that
you need to submit to my authority and
you need to pay me a yearly tribute.
And apparently Porus refused. I will not
submit to your authority. I will not
become your vasal and I will not pay you
a single rupee
and that's why the battle happened. So
apparently the Greek forces are on the
west bank of the indust and the in and
the porous porous his forces are on the
east bank of the river and apparently
porus had less soldiers than the Greeks
30,000 which is a big big number. Was it
that that that powerful a king really?
uh most likely he was a district level
king okay some kind but the Greeks
obviously have overinflated his figures
so so apparently Porus had about 30,000
or so soldiers and the Greeks had
possibly around 40,000 soldiers and then
the battle happens and apparently the
son of Porus is killed in one of the
skirmishes and then there's a proper
battle the Indians have elephants the
Greeks don't have elephants but they
have great soldiers and tremendous
horses and uh and the Indians fight well
and Alexander is injured and his horse
Busales is killed. But eventually the
Greeks being superior people, they
defeat the Indians and King Porus is uh
is is is captured and brought in front
of Alexander. And Alexander says, "Now
you will pay me tribute." And Porus
says, "No, I will still not pay you
tribute because as you know, I'm a king
and it's a king's duty to take care of
his land and so on." So Alex so
allegedly Alexander asks Porus, "How
should I treat you? How should I deal
with you?" And Pora says deal with me
the way you would deal with a king.
Alexander is super impressed by the guy.
And he gives back his territory and he
makes him a local satrap. You are now my
vasal. You have your territory back. I'm
so impressed with you. That sort of
thing. So that's the Greek story. And
that's the battle of the vitashta, the
battle of the hedaspies.
What really happened?
We have no idea. Why do Indian records
not mention
any of this? Indian records don't
mention Porus. They don't mention
Alexander. They don't mention the Yanas
before Silucus arrives,
right? Why is it? Look,
there could be multiple reasons for it.
Maybe one reason is that our
universities and libraries were all were
all destroyed
during the Turk occupation of India. And
maybe the records may have existed but
you know the destruction of the
libraries the burning of the libraries
destroyed the records. Maybe that's one
reason why there are no records of uh
the Greeks of of Porus and Alexander in
Indian records.
U we do have some surviving records from
Tibet and China and uh so bumi and Sri
Lanka because you know the the people of
these these regions they copied Indian
records and and and
stored them. So whatever we know
a lot of what we know about ancient
India comes from these foreign records
which are copies of Indian records in
the local languages but once again
there's no there is no mention of
Alexander or Porus
and you know we have Takashila in the
region Takashila is nearby the great
university so obviously you had
historians scholars and whatnot over
there and there was a significant
military presence to to safeguard
Takshila and there's no mention of
Alexander or Porus or thing. So most
likely what happened is that Porus must
have been a small district level
chieftain
and it's also possible that he may have
defeated the Greeks
and that's probably why the Greeks the
Greek soldiers said that we will no
longer go for further east. We don't
want to tangle with the Indians if this
is what we have to face when we deal
with someone like Poras. Further inwards
further east we have the Nanda Empire.
what will they do with us? Right? And
that's why they mutinied and they forced
Alexander to go back to Macedon. But he
could not reach Macedon. He was he died
in Babylon. And that's a whole different
story. We will not go into that. So
there are multiple reasons why Porus or
and Alexander may not have been why they
are not mentioned in Indian records.
Maybe the records did exist. They were
mentioned perhaps but the records were
destroyed by the Turks. or maybe they
were not mentioned at all. So in case
they were not mentioned at all, why is
it so? Because the Greeks did not have
any impact on India. They did all kind
of barbaric atrocities in in in uh
Persia and on the outskirts of India
which is the the the the borderlands of
Persia and India. But they never really
made any real impact on India proper
on the Nanda Empire and and the big
kingdoms that existed in western India.
So uh from our perspective it was like
nothing
nothing important.
If Alexander had tried coming let's say
to Sarashtra and tried coming further
inland inwards into India then maybe our
restor may have recorded the guy but he
would not have succeeded in doing even
that. So you know that that's the thing
that's the deal. Uh so Field Marsh
Marshall George Zhukov of the USSR,
he was of the opinion that Alexander
actually lost to the to this local king
and this defeat was what triggered off
the set of events that culminated in the
death of Alexander.
So most likely it was a disastrous Greek
defeat that happened at the hands of
this local chieftain.
Okay. Nirvana Shanks says, "Why did the
Bronze Age collapse happen everywhere?
Greece, the Hittites, Egypt, all of
them, and all at the same time. And what
was really behind this, right? Okay,
let's take this question and let's go to
the map once again. Bronze Age collapse.
We're talking about the 1200s BC.
between 1200 BC and 1100 BC is where
this bronze is when this bronze age
collapse happens and it happens in this
region the Mediterranean region.
So we have Mcanian Greece, we have uh
the new kingdom in Egypt, you have the
Hittite Empire in Anatolia.
Um
and uh the Mitani Empire in present day
Syria and so on, right?
uh you have the Louvians, you have the
Minoans
and all of these
uh kingdoms, empires, civilizations,
whatever you want to call it, they all
disintegrate very rapidly
around the 1200s BC.
All of them disappear.
So clearly something happened that
affected them all at the same time.
And that's the question, what exactly
happened? So
we should also remember it's around this
time that you have climate change in
India as well by the way
because the Saraswati has kind of dried
out to a significant extent by 1500 BC
and then by 1200 BC you have Indians
migrating out of the of the Saraswati
Hindu region abandoning the great cities
that we call Harpa Mahindo and so on and
moving to other parts of India and some
of them moving westwards outside of
India going out forever.
So there was some such activity even
happening in India around this time 1200
BC. But let's focus on the Mediterranean
region and the so-called bronze age
collapse. What happened? So like I said
myian Greece disappears. It it
collapses. The Egyptian 10th dynasty
endures collapse. the Hittite kingdom
empire the the Mitani kingdom or empire
the the Louvians the Minoans all
collapse at the same time
so one of the things that's recorded I
mean there are books about this okay I
have books but I'll not open the book
now so one of the things that is
recorded is that there was there was a
bunch of people called the sea peoples s
e a peoples they were invaders who got
came from god knows where and they
invaded Egypt, they invaded all Greece,
they invaded everybody. So it was some
kind of
power,
maritime power who came from the sea,
maybe from the Mediterranean and invaded
all these kingdoms and created complete
chaos and havoc in the in all these
kingdoms, in all these different
cultures. That's number one. Number two,
there was drought and possibly famine at
this time. Climate change, climate
change, like I said. Number three, there
could have been earthquakes and things
like that. And there the and scholars
even said that there could have been
pandemics like plague or something that
devastated the region at this time and
maybe earthquakes also because the
region is kind of sometimes prone to
earthquakes. We recently had earthquakes
in Turkey which is kind of this region.
Turkey is obviously ancient Greece. It
is by the way. Yeah. So maybe tectonic
tectonic activity you have volcanism in
the region you know kira
etc. Volcanic volcanic activity has
happened in the past.
So maybe it was a combination most
likely of factors
that created a perfect storm. We don't
have one factor that we can think of
that caused a collapse of all these
different cultures.
Any research that you study for example.
Okay. Do you want a book recommendation?
I could do that. Give me a second. Be
right back.
Okay, book recommendation. Let us do a
book recommendation very quickly. Ah,
okay. Here we are. So, book
recommendation is this one.
This is a book by Eric C. Klene 1177 BC,
the year civilization collapsed. By the
way, it did not collapse in India or
China. But yeah, obviously it's a
euroentric perspective. But if you want
to understand what happened uh when it
comes to um the so-called bronze age
collapse uh this question here, then
this is a good book, good reference
book. It kind of goes into the details
of you know essentially it it says there
a perfect storm of calamities like I
like I was saying.
So yeah, so I'll not go and read the
book right now. It's something I read a
while ago. So it's a it's a combination
of multiple factors. This the sea
peoples. who came and ravaged all these
all these cultures. Secondly,
drought and famine and climate change.
Thirdly, possibly earthquakes, fourth,
possibly the disruption of trade routes
between the between all these cultures
because of the sea peoples um maybe
plague and and pandemics. So all of this
a perfect storm collapsed these cultures
and maybe see imagine like this imagine
this for example completely hypothetical
thought experiment. I am not saying this
should happen. Okay? In case someone
wants to misport like that, there are
lots of people who want to do that. This
is a complete hypothetical fictitious
thought experiment
to contextualize what we're discussing
here. Imagine something happens to the
United States.
H the most dominant country in the world
and the
the country whose technology everybody
uses today. Imagine the US for some
example becomes crippled.
All their servers go crash. All these
websites and platforms that use
disappear and uh the security or
whatever security architecture, military
architecture they provide to the world
disappears. Then the world will be
thrown into chaos. There's going to be
outbreaks of wars everywhere. I promise
you that it's going to cause complete
chaos. So maybe something similar
happened in the eastern Mediterranean
region. Maybe the dominant power
collapsed and that caused a chain
reaction. A domino effect everything
collapsed.
Maybe they were all interdependent for
trade, for supplies, for food stuffs,
for other things. And the collapse of
one part of the chain collapsed
everything else because of also we have
in ongoing invasions by the sea peoples
and also drought and famine, maybe
earthquakes, maybe pandemic, maybe. So
essentially it's most likely a perfect
storm a combination of all these all
these factors that came together and
just destroyed all these civilizations
in the region did not affect us by the
way right we had the climate change
factor in western northern western India
people around this time abandoned these
great cities these great metropolitan
cities like Rakari Kalibangan so-called
Mohinda so-cala and so on and other ones
others also and moved to other parts of
India and this whole region became
desertified the tar region and so on. So
you had climate change which was
affecting India at the time but the
other factors weren't affecting India.
So it looks like it was a combination of
factors that caused the so-called bronze
age collapse.
Next,
Amisha says, "Why is the term
colonialism often limited the European
empires since the age of discoveries,
so-called age of discoveries? Weren't
ancient empires such as Rome, China, or
Persia also colonialist?"
Uh, the Persians were the colonizers.
I'm not sure. I would not categorize the
Persians, the the Aimeirate Empire as a
colonial empire. They were certainly
expansionists.
They were a hegemonic empire but they
did not engage in what we call
colonialism and let me explain I'll come
to what I mean by that. So I would not
consider Persia to be a colonial empire.
It was an imperial power. It was a
hegemonic power but not a colonial
power. China was it a colonial power?
Not really. It is a colonial power today
kind of. Today it's become a colonial
power. It has settler colonized Tibet
and Manuria and Shinjang and whatn not
inner Mongolia as well. Never Chinese
territories but it has settler colonized
all the territories today. Like I keep
saying the Chinese
the hero worship the United States. They
want to emulate the US in whatever the
US does. So that's a different story.
Now Rome was it a colonial empire? You
could say it was.
You could say it was. Yeah. So, so the
question main question Amisha is asking
is why is the term colonialism often
limited to European empire since the in
in the past 500 years. It's because they
don't want to use the word occupation
which is a nasty word. Do you ever see
me use the word British colonialism
the British colonization of India? Do I
do do I use that? I use the term the
British occupation of India because what
they did was settler occup was
occupation. It was not settler
colonization. It was extractive
colonization. It was the British
occupation of India. The word occupation
has brutal connotations. Which is why
they don't want to use that word for
what the Europeans did in the past 500
or so years. That's why you they use
this nice term colonization.
We made colonies.
Indians also when they hear the word col
colon colonial era they think of a nice
peaceful era. They have no idea of the
barbarity and the brutality that was
perpetrated on India.
So the reason this term is used is
because they want to
essentially whitewash the barbaric
crimes the Europeans uh perpetrated on
the occupied lands which is the whole of
Africa which is India which is so much
more.
It's to whitewash the brutality. It's to
whitewash the genocide. is to whitewash
for example uh
the ethnic cleansing for what like what
happened in the Americas ethnic
cleansing. Um so it's it's the objective
of using colon the word colonialism
is to whitewash the crimes of the
Europeans to make it look sound nice and
civilized. Colonialism is civilized.
Occupation is brutal and barbaric. So we
don't use the term occupation.
Royal Okub says how do we classify an
empire if it's Indian or not. Can
distant Hindu kingdoms like the Mitani
Empire be classified as Indian or
Indianized?
Well, it depends on what definition you
use.
Very simple. We had the British Empire,
didn't we?
We at at the peak of the occupation of
India, you had about 20,000 British
officials who were in India,
you had about 800,000 British people
which were the extended extended
families of the occupiers.
But the officials which is the uh
colonial officials, occupation officials
which is the soldiers and bureaucrats,
British and and administrators. That's
just 20,000.
But yet India was part of the British
Empire, wasn't it? Right? We were part
of the British Empire at the time and so
were Singapore and Malaysia and whatever
else the British had occupied. So was
Egypt. It was all part of the British
Empire. So we were part of the British
Empire. So from that perspective, the
Mitani Empire was an Indian Empire. But
there's something different here. There
is there's a nuance that you have to
think of. When the British occupied
India, they were reporting to London,
their viceroy or whatever it was, their
governor general or whatever who was
sitting in Delhi or wherever, he or he
would report to the crown in London.
They would take orders from the crown in
London. He would serve the crown in in
London. The Mitani Empire did not serve
any headquarters in the subcontinent.
They were completely independent.
They possibly did not even have any
connections anymore with the Indian
subcontinent. So from that perspective,
it's not Indian. Maybe it's Indianized,
but maybe not maybe not Indian entirely.
It's an Indianized kingdom with an
Indo-arian or Arian or Indian Sanskrit
speaking uh royalty and aristocracy. But
the con people were the local huran
speaking people.
>> So the metanic kingdom depending on how
you see it is either an Indian kingdom
or an Indianized kingdom or maybe
definitely Indianized for sure. Um yeah
that's how you that's how you would
classify it.
Yajj Navalia says was the bifphasic
sleep pattern wherein people slept early
first sleep woke around midnight for a
while and returned to sleep return to
bed or second sleep prevalent in
pre-industrial societies. How did this
sleep pattern change with the dominance
of artificial lighting in the modern
era?
So there used to be something called
bifphasics sleep at least in Europe. It
is recorded in Europe before the advent
of artificial lighting in the industrial
age. So people in Europe would go to
sleep by sunset.
By sunset you would have complete
darkness everywhere. People could light
fires or whatever but you did not have
any street lights or any such thing. You
had no light pollution in the sky. The
sky was proper pitch black. You would
see stars. The stars you would see them
in great detail. If it was a moonlit
night, yeah, you could see more, but
overall you had proper darkness at
light. So people typically in Europe
would go to sleep by sunset. Let's say
7:00 p.m. Hypothetically, different
parts of Europe, you have different
different depending on the latitude,
etc., but let's say they went to sleep
by sunset.
Then they would sleep for a few hours.
Then they would wake up around midnight,
around around 12:00 p.m. or so, roughly
around that time. And then they would be
awake for a while, maybe an hour or so,
and they would do whatever whatever they
did. I that's that's not important. So
they would sleep until around 12. They
would be awake for an hour or so and
then they would go back to sleep again
and they would wake up at sunrise
and maybe that that period in between
when where they were awake, maybe it was
1 hour, maybe it was like a couple of
hours, maybe two, three hours, whatever
it was. So you had two different
distinct separate phases of sleep broken
up by a period period of being awake in
between. So it was a bifphasic sleep
pattern that was prevalent in Europe
before the industrial age. Maybe it was
prevalent for thousands of years before
the industrial age which in the
industrial age brought with it street
lights and all that. Initi initially you
had u oil powered street lights then you
had gas powered street lights eventually
electricity powered street lights and
artificial lighting in everyone's house.
So eventually
you know artificial lighting became the
norm and because of that the bifphasic
sleep pattern was combined or fused
into a single sleep pattern a single 8
hour roughly uh period of sleep. So that
is what the deal was in Europe. Now did
other cultures or societies have
bifphasic sleep patterns? The Chinese
and the Indians also had bifphasic sleep
patterns but different. The Chinese and
Indians would sleep for a couple of
hours in the afternoon.
Okay. Take a nap. The Italians also have
this practice. They call it the siesta.
Siesta. Yes. Siesta. So in India and
China also people typically
especially when India was still
civilized and not occupied with
foreigners people would sleep for a
couple of hours in the afternoon sleep
it off and then so in India we did not
have a bifphasic night sleep pattern
they sleep by sunset and then sleep for
four five hours and wake up for a couple
of hours and sleep again no as far as we
know that did not exist in India there's
no record of that and not neither in
China so the two big Asian civilizations
we did not have this but the Europeans
had it. Why is it so? I'm not sure why.
Uh but yeah it end this this pattern
this bifphasic sleep pattern ended with
the advent of artificial lighting and
with the advent of artificial lighting
people started staying staying awake
much later. So earlier if people would
have slept by 700 p.m. with the art
advent of artificial lighting you could
stay awake all night if you wanted which
is not advisable at all. So maybe people
started sleeping late maybe by 9:10 p.m.
or whatever and then they would wake up
at dawn. So then this entire bifphasic
sleep pattern disappeared. It was
replaced by a single sleep phase and
roughly 8 hours sleep phase. And today I
suppose people don't sleep 8 hours
anymore
because people have blue light in front
of their eyes all day all night. They're
looking at this, looking at this and
then that that affects the quality of
sleep and then people sleep five what
five six hours and people find it
glorious that we sleep five six hours
because you know I sleep less work more
it's going to affect the quality of your
life anyway so yeah that's the deal
Nirvana Shanks says in dealing with the
Turk invasions around 1000 AD could
Indian rulers have remained defensive or
would a more proactive offensive
strategy have been better to eliminate
the threat permanently.
Okay, interesting question which brings
in geographical uh aspects as well as
political aspects of India and the
region at the time. So first of all we
have to remember around 1000 AD India
was no longer uh politically unified
under a single emperor. It was no longer
a simple single empire as was the case
during the Morian era or the Kusan era
or the Gupta era or maybe even the Kota
era right when you had one single
massively powerful imperial power that
uh that controlled a major portion of
the subcontinent's territory and maybe
beyond the subcontinent. Um around 1000
AD we did not have this. We had
kingdoms.
Kingdoms. So India was no longer united.
India was broken up into kingdoms. Same
people all related to each other. But we
have different kingdoms and we have our
own territory and we will jealously
protect that and we'll fight each other
and we will have this petty jealousies
and rivalries. That was the deal around
1000 AD. So no kingdom was powerful
enough at this time to even defeat its
neighboring kingdoms in India and unify
the whole subcontinent. Again,
understand this first of all. So, you
don't have any genuinely powerful
kingdom.
They're all kind of there's a balance of
power so to say between these various
kingdoms. So, they are always worried
about the next king. He might come and
take my territory, take bites out of my
territory. So, they were always guarding
their borders and that was the deal.
So because of and and none of them were
powerful enough to defeat everybody
else. Now the Turks they come from the
northwest the Kyber pass
and the Turks they are this nomadic
tribalistic society
and they cover vast distances very
rapidly and they are unified under the
Goris and the Gnavis and whatn not. So
that was a very different threat
and it made sense. I mean you know
sitting to sitting over here in front of
the map in our air conditioned rooms in
our armchairs it's very easy to imagine
that why didn't any Indian king think
about it like this that did we go and
you know cut the head of the snake off
go to the root the source of the problem
and eradicate the problem. Why didn't
they think about it? First of all, we do
not have maps the way we do today. See,
today we we we can do this. We can look
what what on earth is that. Okay, let's
do this. So, we can look here. Okay, so
see we we let's say I am a king in in
Rajasthan for example. And I have this
issue that comes in all the time from
you know northwest from from Gandhar.
Where is Gore? Where is Gazny? Wherever
it is. So these guys they come from
there. So let me once and on and for all
go all the way to Gore and Gazni and
then wipe the ground clean with from the
of these barbarians. Let me liberate
Gandhar and then maybe I can even rule
Gandhar.
The problem is we have all these little
kingdoms in the way and they will not
allow any of the big kings any of the
kings to come and cross their territory
on their way to Gandhar. And if let's
say I'm a king and I will leave my
kingdom, take my army, take the
permission of all the other kings and go
all the way to Gandhar. In the
meanwhile, will somebody else not take
my kingdom?
That was the problem.
So theoretically they should have done
it. Yes. Gone to the source of the
problem, the root of the problem and and
fixed it. But practically it was not
possible at all.
All right. The world is a complicated
place.
You know, cows aren't spherical. In
physics, we say that cows are spherical.
You know, we consider ideal conditions.
But in the real world, there are all
kinds of complications. Those
complications prevent things from
happening the way we would like them to
happen. So, that was the issue sir. That
was the issue.
Amisha says, "What made Saddam Hussein
think that he had any chance of winning
against a giant coalition all by himself
in the Gulf War?" Uh what makes us think
that he actually thought this?
How do we know Saddam Hussein thought
that he could win this? Has he did he
ever give any indication that he
believed that he could win the war?
Did he even want a war? He never wanted
a war.
See, Iraq was an American vasal.
The Americans used Iraq to bleed Iran in
the 1980s during the Iran Iraq war.
So, Saddam Hussein was an American
vasal. He was a he was an American
asset.
And then in 1990 or whatever, he goes
and asks the Americans, you know, this
this Kuwaitis, they are stealing my oil.
We have oil wells. We have a border
between Iraq and Kuwait. And the
Kuwaitis are not drilling deep down
straight down. They're dealing side
drilling sideways and siphoning oil oil
off from my territories from from oil
wells in my in my territory
and they have been doing this for a long
time. I need to teach them a lesson.
That's what Saddam Hussean told the
Americans. So he said, "Hey Americans,
you okay if I go and take Kuwait?
You okay with that?
Will you have an issue if I do that?"
They said, "Go ahead. Go ahead, Saddam.
Go ahead." So Saddam goes and invades
Kuwait. And then the Americans say, "How
how dare you."
So the Americans threw Saddam Hussein
under the bus.
The Americans wanted direct control of
Iraq's oil wealth.
They they were tired of Saddam Hussein.
He had no he no longer served any
purpose for them apparently. So they
gave him the green light to go and
invade Kuwait. And the moment he did
that they said you are a very naughty
boy now we will invade you and they
created this big coalition invasion
force and they invaded Iraq in 20ou in
and they must have killed I don't know
how many millions of Iraqis but Saddam
Hussein still remained in power until
2003 when some few more million Iraqis
were killed and Saddam Hussein was the
one to be captured and and executed.
So Saddam Hussein did not ever have any
intention of fighting a war against the
whole world.
He was an American wasal and he took
permission from the Americans before
invading Kuwait and the Americans
trapped him.
They put him in a corner and then they
did what they did. That's what happened
in the 1990s. 91 was the Gulf War, the
first oil war so to say.
Amisha once again difference between
settlement and colonization.
See let's say I start a space company
which is way better than Elon Musk's
SpaceX and I
start launching 1,000 people per rocket
launch
into space. Now you can't simply launch
people into space. You have to have some
habitation, right? So I will first go to
the moon and I'll create this apartment
complexes on the moon. Okay, that's all
hypothetical. I will create first
apartment complexes on the moon. Let's
say I can accommodate 100,000 people,
one lakh. Then I'll start taking people
from the earth and settling them there.
That is called settlement. Then I will
go to the to to Mars and eventually I
will settle let's say 500,000 people
there. That is called settlement.
Now let's say I go to Pakistan,
okay?
And I take over the country
and then I start exploiting the
resources and taking stuff out of
Pakistan. Oil there or whatever oil and
gas they have, I'll take it out and
bring it to India. Whatever rare earths
they have, I'll mine them and bring it
to India.
uh whatever else they may have, I'll
exploit all of that and bring all that
all those resources to India
and I I will have some people my my
military and my officials who will
administer Pakistan and keep the
Pakistanis under my boot. This is called
colonization.
That's the difference between settlement
and colonization. Settlement means
you're settling in a place where nobody
else exists.
Colonization means you are subjugating
the people who exist and exploiting
them. That is the difference between
settlement and colonization.
Yajjnalika says, "Is it true that the
Gupta Empire was larger in area than the
present day Republic of India? If yes,
one may get deceived if one just looks
at the maps of both and compares the
areas visually. I think the Gupta Empire
at its peak at its peak was larger in
land area uh than the present day
Republic of India and we can
let's let's see if it is actually true.
What does Wikipedia our good friend have
to say? Our super unreliable Wikipedia.
What's it say this time? So let's just
Google India. Okay,
not cricket. I want to see the Wikipedia
entry about India. Here we are. So let
us see the Wikipedia entry for India. It
must have some area somewhere. Land uh
area land area
3287263,287,000
square kilmters 3287. Okay. Now let us
look at Gupta Empire.
Remember the thing in the number in mind
38 what is it once again let me see 328
3287 okay now Gupta Empire 3287 3287
let's remember what is the land area of
the Gupta Empire 3287 was a thing
Maharaj Dhi is fine do we have a land
area somewhere 3287 land area 3500 which
is bigger than 3287
so even Wikipedia agrees with what I
just said that the Gupta Empire empire
that period of our history we had a
greater land area our the Gupta Empire
covered a greater land area than the
current day present day republic of
Bhart
okay indeed so even Wikipedia agrees
with that
Mr. Scared cat. Scaredy cat. Are you? Uh
the question is what punishments were
given for corruption, crime against
women and abuse of power during India's
great empire such as the Morian empire,
the Chola, the Kushan, Ashoka's reign.
Maybe we need those today to restore
fairness and discipline in present day
India.
That's a topic I'm not going into. But
let's discuss punishments. I'm not sure
about the Kushan era because we don't
have detailed records of uh legal
procedures and and crime and punishment
during the Kushan era. But we do have a
fantastic resource from the Morian era,
the Art Shastra.
So the Art Shastra tells you in detail
what kind of punishments were meed out
for various crimes.
And if you talk about the time of
emperor Ashok Ashoka's reign, that's
once again the Morian era, right? Ashoka
was the most powerful emperor of the
Morian um empire, Morian dynasty or
Morian period of our history, which is
about 2,300
years ago or so.
So u if you read the ara shastra it
tells you what punishments are are given
for what crimes like 30 40 crimes are
mentioned you know administrative petty
corruption crimes and all that. Um
so typically if if somebody an official
was corrupt
and he had embezzled some money he would
have to pay a fine of 10 times that.
Okay, the fine would be 10 time that and
if it was a repeat repeat offender it
would be end of story, goodbye, death
penalty. Um, so and for bribery and
other stuff there were heavy fines
sometimes physical punishment means you
know be you know beating with hitting
with uh cane or whatever. Um crimes
against women I think the punishments
were harsher. I think during the war era
it was death pen death death pen death
death penalty
uh for sexual assault I'm sure it was
the death penalty I'm not sure for other
things what it was um when it comes to
abuse of power okay let's let's
understand what is abuse of power
if you are abusing power during the
morian
empire's era it means that you are a
person in power who is abusing power now
if you are a person in power.
It means that you serve
the Maharaja Dhiraj, the emperor of
India
and you are acting
on his behalf, right? You are you hold
power on behalf of the emperor. If you
abuse that power,
if you go against, if you fail to carry
out the emperor's will
and if you do something that the emperor
has which goes against what the emperor
has decreed, that's abuse of power,
right? The emperor has said that you are
an official in his in his court in his
administration and you are supposed to
carry out these duties and that is how
you will use your power. If you abuse
your power, it means you're going
against the wishes and the will of the
emperor. I promise you the punishment
won't be very lenient for that.
If you're lucky, you will escape with a
gigantic fine and and physical
punishment, corporal punishment. But
typically if you abused power in the
during the morian era, especially during
the time of Shri Ashoke,
I think it was the death penalty
straight away.
And maybe if the if if your crime was
you know significantly
u heenous then you would first be
tortured before you were killed
especially during the time of emperor
Ashok because he was a pretty harsh
emperor. He was fond of well he was well
he was what he was right. So yeah, you
did not want to do that. If you did did
that, you would if you abused power and
you were in a high position, it was a
guaranteed death sentence.
So that's how it was during the Chola
era. How how were things? The Cholas
used to have uh Dharma Sabhas and all
that.
And uh for domestic crimes and all the
dharma sabhas would decide what would
happen what punishment would be given.
If you let's say you are a husband who
beat your wife then there would be some
kind of penalty that you would have to
pay. Um if you did corruption or
whatever you would have to give a hefty
fine to the local temple or something.
But if you abuse power once again which
went against the emperor's wishes then I
think the the punishment would be much
more severe in that case. Um that's the
Chola uh that's relevant to the Chola
Empire obviously Kushan Empire I'm not
sure but all these empires there would
not be strong empires if if they did not
have very strict adherance to the rule
of law and very clear punishments.
The punishments not necessarily need to
be very harsh, but they have to be
implemented
uh in a way that is like guaranteed, you
know, that if you break the law, you're
going to guaranteed to be punished. And
that's what we had. We had high
standards back in the day. Uh I shall
say no, nothing beyond that because I
deal with history, geopolitics, and
science and I don't deal with current
politics. So, okay.
Raptor Babu that's is quite a name
Raptor Babu. Raptor Babu says is Europe
even a continent in a geographical
sense. Are the a idea of white European
west artificially introduced? Because
white people look light brown or or
brown pink or red or not generally
white. Why do they even we even call
them white? When I saw your
understanding America episode, it made
me think that we they need these layers
of identity unifying them all to stop
wars amongst them while they try while
they try to do the reverse and try to
balconize India like places. What are my
thoughts? Okay.
Uh we will deal with the question of
whether Europe is a continent in a
geographical scale from a sense geog
geographic sense. I mean if you're
talking about geography, it's always
that I'll go to the map. So let's take a
look at the map.
Do you what is a continent? See, Africa
is a continent. It's clearly separate
from all everything else. There is a
little bit of connection here which has
now been severed artificially through
this west canal. And historically, Egypt
was regarded as an Asian civilization by
the way, but whatever. So, Africa is
clearly a continent. Australia clearly a
continent. Antarctica clearly a
continent. U North and South America,
you could say these are two separate
continents. There's a very little small
sliver of land which is the entire
nation which comes in the way but fine
okay two separate continents. Now when
it comes to
this land mass do you see something
separate called Europe
see India is a peninsula or a
subcontinent clearly it it simply
physically you can see that yeah and
then you have uh this peninsula called
Sakalin sorry this is this is Kamchatka
that is obviously a peninsula
um
Spain is a peninsula Europe but Europe
itself is a peninsula of Eurasia. So
Europe is not a continent geographically
speaking. It is a completely artificial
idea. The Europeans have developed this
sense in their mind that they are
something special and and unique and uh
different. And that's why Europe has to
be considered a separate continent. It's
not a separate continent. Europe is you
could say a peninsula kind of of
Eurasia. It's not a separate continent.
I personally don't recognize it as a
separate continent. Europe. It's a it's
a political region so to say. Even then
you even there you have East Europe,
West Europe, right? And the Western
European nations are the EU and NATO
nations and the Eastern European nations
are the nations that are more closely
allied with Russia and so on. It's a
political concept. The whole concept of
Europe is a political concept.
Uh so it's not really a continent.
Okay.
The Baron Zemo says, "If India had
industrialized before Europe, how might
global power dynamics have changed?
Could India have avoided colonization?
India was the world's first ever fully
industrialized civilization.
India was industrialized before Europe.
When the Europeans came to India, India
was fully industrialized.
This is what the education system has
done to our people.
Our people imagine that India was some
backwater before the Europeans came to
India. The Europeans civilized India.
The Europeans gave us industry. We had
nothing. We were living in half naked in
the trees. Apparently, that's what
Indians imagine. That's what this
godamned education system has done to
Indians. The education system that the
government doesn't want to change. They
want to keep Indians mentally colonized.
This is mental colonization. I don't
blame the person who has asked this
question. This person wants to learn.
I'm glad people want to learn. I'm glad
people have this curiosity. But see what
people are made to believe. India was
the world's first fully industrialized
civilization. When was that? 5,000 years
ago.
3000 BC. India was fully urbanized,
fully industrialized. Do you know this?
You will not know this because you will
not be taught this.
In 1500 AD, India was fully
industrialized.
We did not have electricity.
We did not have computing. We didn't
have cell phones. But we had the best
technologies of the 1500s.
And everybody was employed. There was no
unemployment in India.
And India's GDP was onethird of the
entire world's GDP. At least one/ird.
And none of this is taught to Indians
which is why
I I get all upset.
So my dear friend, India was fully
industrialized before Europe. We were
fully industrialized when the Europeans
were living in caves and eating raw meat
and wearing skins, animal skins.
Did it change power dynamics?
No.
India was fully civilized also. India
was not merely fully civilized. India
was fully industrialized and yet we were
colonized by the Europeans. We were
occupied and destroyed by the Europeans.
So industrialization is not it is
definitely a necessary condition
for for avoiding colonization but it's
not a sufficient condition
for avoiding colonization
and actually it's not even a necess
necessary condition.
Um yeah you need industrial warfare and
all so industrialized warfare. So it's a
necessary condition but not sufficient.
What's sufficient? What what is
sufficient to avoid cronization? You
have to be you have to be able to think
like barbarians
and you have to be able to fight like
them and fight worse than them and that
is something we do not have and that's
why they were able to colonize us. It
begins with the Turks of course. So yeah
that's a deal. Okay 2 hours done. Let's
take a few questions from the live chat
shall we? Yes we shall.
Okay. So in case yes Shoub says we had a
great ship building industry.
Absolutely. We had a great ship building
industry. We had the biggest ships in
the world. I mean Vasco Dama when he
crossed the Cape of Good Hope and he
reached East Africa he thought that he
had the world's biggest ships and he saw
rand random Indian merchants with ships
that were like four times bigger than
his. So yeah.
So it is not enough to be rich. You have
to be powerful and you need to know how
to fight
and more. You have to be unified
and so much more. So anyway, okay. Do we
have questions in the live chat? I will
take some take a few questions. Nah G
says United. Absolutely. G United. Um
okay. Mango whity says for someone who
practically defined linguistics.
Panini doesn't get nearly the
recognition it deserves in India today.
Very few people know him. Why do you
think it is? Because of the education
system.
Maybe your textbook has one a couple of
sentences about paneindi. Who's going to
remember that?
It's a very clever way of doing things.
You know that way you can say that you
know we have mentioned paneindi in our
textbook. Yeah. You got a couple of
sentences, maybe one sentence about him,
that's it. But we mentioned him. So, how
can you say that we we don't mention
him?
It's like, you know, there are these
books that that talk about America's
history, the history of the United
States and they extol the virtues of
Columbus and so on and then they
there'll be one sentence somewhere which
will say that you know the European
occur colonization colonization of of
the Americas it it led to the genocide
of the native Americans. There'll be one
word genocide and one sentence about
that somewhere in a in a 2,000word
textbook and they'll say no no no look
there look on that page we have
mentioned that they a genocide did
happen. So we are not whitewashing
history. It will be buried under some
some you know massive verbiage.
So yeah the problem is the education
system. That's why Indians don't know
about panini.
Okay
feel strong man says counter my point
sir we are not doing any military. I'm
not countering anyone's points.
Uh Rabi says what's the role of s worker
in the independence movement? I have not
studied the the life history of Shri
Sawar in any any great detail. Uh so I
will not be able to speak about that. I
am not an expert in the independence
movement. I have not studied various
great personalities like Mr. Sauurkar,
Mr. Gandhi, Dr. Ambedkar and whoever
else may exist, Shinu G. I know things
in from a macros macroscopic perspective
but I don't know the specific details. I
don't know the the exact details of
exactly how things went. So
yeah, uh Pratana says, "I'm testing
something." All right, sir. No issues.
Harshai says, "Duh. Do films have a
long-term impact on the human mind?"
Like I watched yesterday,
a movie I watched yesterday, K1
showed theme of oppressor and oppress
those who had build temples bad. Of
course, movies have a huge impact.
when you are when you are young you love
movies I love movies even today so
movies so when you are young when you
are 15 16 years old when you are 12
years old you are super impressionable
and it's easier to impress someone
through the audiovisisual medium than
through books
so movies can can burn images into your
mind forever
so movies have a huge impact are a great
tool of propaganda And the most powerful
tool the United States for example has
geopolitically is Hollywood.
It's so easy to to mislead people by
making movies.
And movies have been used to to portray
Hinduism as evil. And that's why lots of
people believe Hinduism is an evil
religion. Your own people, our own
people, Hindus themselves believe that
our ancestors are very cruel, very
cruel, very oppressive. Yeah. So movies
are are a massive propaganda tool. Pan
Shri Hasha says why is there no ruins of
Indian king's palaces
while Rome Egypt and others preserve
their ancient monuments why couldn't
India do that what happened to the
shungas Gupta Moria etc rulers palaces
well to a very large extent we did not
have rulers who lived in massive palaces
for example you see it's possible that
that rulers from older eras their
palaces could not have survived possibly
because how long does a building
survived thousand years 2,000 years
we've had history goes going back many
more thousand years before that we have
cities great cities like Rakiari Birana
Kalibangan Mohenjadaro Harapa and so on
where you don't find palaces at all we
still have the outlines of those cities
and the buildings and all that we know
that we had multi-story buildings there
we have the public works the the
drainage systems the canals the the the
bathous and the assembly halls and
whatnot there's simply no palace
Does it mean that we did not have kings
at the time or does it mean that kings
lived like ordinary people? What does it
mean? We're not quite sure. Most likely
we had some kind of quasi democratic
system during the that period of time.
Uh the more era we had emperors. So
obviously we so what was the deal? Did
did the emperors did not have palaces?
Maybe some emperors had palaces. Maybe
Chad Gupta may have had a palace. Maybe
Ashok would have had a palace. I suppose
maybe the palace don't doesn't stand
anymore. Um say it's 2 and a half
thousand years roughly before today.
It's very hard for any building to stand
that long, right?
Um
what about the shungas? The shungas they
would also have ruled out of
partutrautra
is in ruins today the old city and we
haven't really bothered to excavate it.
You don't even find any any colored
pictures of partiputra today. The
excavated parts of Patiputra it's
completely neglected the Gupta era once
again partiputra and then was it Matura
wherever it was
so once again our ASI has done nothing
all they're doing is busy they're busy
maintaining muggal monuments from the
muggal kingdom
uh yeah so it is so it is true that many
Indian kings did not maintain palaces
for example if you look at uh if you
If you examine or consider something
more recent like the Marata Empire, it
was an empire.
They had forts
which are military fortifications.
Forts typically on hills. They were
called duras, right? Dura. But did the
Marata emperors have palaces?
No.
You had some Rajput kings who had
palaces that were built after the
Vasalage period of the Rajputs.
And you have these princely kingdoms
which are all British vasals who had
palaces. Sure. But the true sovereign
kings and emperors of India it's hard to
find their palaces if they if they had
any. So it's it's a big question. Looks
like many of the Indian kings and
emperors did not really maintain massive
palaces. Looks like that.
Godliness says for you what is the
history of science? How back in history
will you date science and which
scientific experiment or innovation will
you select as being earliest in the
recorded history? Um
what's the history of science is the
history of science is the history of
scientific thought.
It begins so where does science begin?
Science begins in philosophy.
What is philosophy?
Philosophy is the systematic or
systematic.
It's it's how to how you configure your
thoughts systematically. How you
organize your thoughts systematically
and and and you follow rules of thought.
So philosophy is essentially the quest
for uncovering the laws of the universe.
So you're looking for patterns and
regularities and you're following rules
in your inquiry. You don't just randomly
inquire things and you don't randomly
believe something right and then that is
extended into what becomes the laws of
science and the scientific method.
So for example in philosophy
you have patterns and regularities that
you are looking for but philosophy deals
with
objects and phenomena which may not be
material objects and phenomena.
Philosophy considers things such as the
soul atma. The atma is not a physical
object. Philosophy thinks considers
things like morality and ethics. These
are not physical
phenomena or objects. So philosophy
deals with abstract concepts which are
non-physical.
But if you remove the abstractness and
the non-physicality from philosophy, it
becomes science.
So where does the history of science
begin? It begins with the schools, the
Indian philosophical schools of thought.
For example,
which was it? Vashik was it? I have done
a whole five minute video on this.
Uh
it was Maharashi Kan who said that the
entire
nature is composed of atoms
right Kana atoms. So that's the
atomistic theory or or the first to say
quantum theory kind of goes back god
knows how many thousands of years. So I
think it's it's I would say it's there
that u the history of science begins.
Uh it's it's when you disregard the the
non-material aspects of philosophy and
you focus purely on the material based
on the scientific method. That's where
science begins.
U so yeah that that's that for me is
where the history of science begins. And
uh which experiment or innovation?
I'm not sure about that.
Which experiment are in? Okay, let me
give you an example.
Find me an older one. Okay,
let me show you. Google.
Okay. Bor zoom
supernova.
This is ancient rock art from from
northern India from Kashmir
which shows you a sky chart
and there are two suns in the sky. And
if you go back to the time the time
period when this rock was this rock art
was done you will you will see that
there was a supernova a star that
exploded exactly what this this
mentions. So this is not some hunting
scene. It is actually a sky chart with
with constellations with Orion the
hunter and so on and and it it records a
supernova eruption that happened about 5
6,000 years ago. So maybe that's the
first observ observational evidence of
of with some kind of a scientific u
background perhaps.
Okay. Um let's take the next question
couple more. My opinion on bridge was
responsible for the no the person who
was responsible for the decline of the
USSR was Gorbachev.
You could say that you know standards
started declining during BRNV's time.
The decline of the USSR, if you really
want to give a date to it, it's the
death of Stalin.
Things start going downwards from that
time onwards. It is what it is. I'm not
a great fan of Stalin. He we you don't
want a ruler like Stalin. You don't want
one like him. But he's the guy who made
the USSR what what it became a
superpower. And the decline started with
the death of Stalin. So you have Krishv
and so on and so on. Eventually BRNAV so
every new leader the the standards
decline slightly and with Gorbachov just
takes a nose dive and yeah
uh I look like Brnav wearing sunglasses
how dare you I don't look Russian
okay so that's how I see it right Hitman
91 thank you very much thank you okay
we're done with the super chats and
vi says aren't we ourselves responsible
for the current situation of bat when
you were born what was India's GDP
let's say let's assume you're 20 years
old okay roughly so it would mean you
were born in 2005 what was India's GDP
in 2005 1 billion or sorry 1 trillion
less
are you responsible for the India's GDP
rate I mean what India's GDP was when
when you were born
then today India's GDP is 4 something
trillion are you responsible for the
increase in India's GDP you see the
common person is not responsible for for
whatever condition or state the the
country is in. It is the leadership and
the administration which is entirely
responsible for whatever shape the
country is in good or bad.
We imagine that we are responsible for
everything. We are told that we are
responsible for everything.
No, that's not the case. That is not
true at all. India standards have
declined because of a thousand years of
foreign occupation and because of the
standards the Nuvian and subsequent
regimes have had. It is not the fault of
the people of India. My dear friends,
please every morning wake up and tell
yourself it's not our fault that India
is in the shape that whatever plight it
is in today.
Okay.
Okay. Okay, let's take maybe one one or
two questions more and then we can be
done.
Um,
okay, let's take this one by Naj Desai
Muhammad Gaddafi. How was he providing
his countrymen incredible free schemes
by seemingly having no external debts?
What was his economic structure and how
did it make it work? I am not sure about
that. I have not looked into the uh
economy of Libya under Colonel Colon
Colonel Mohammer Gaddafi. I have not
looked into what I know is that there
was no debt. What I know is that he gave
a lot of these fantastic schemes to his
people. Education was free apparently,
especially for girls and so on. I'm not
sure exactly how it was done. I've not
studied that. But yeah, he did that. He
was able to achieve that. He did so much
good for his people. All he wanted was
that people the West leaves him alone.
Leave my country alone. That's it.
Okay. Uh Charlie Kirk, I have no opinion
about that. Then we're talking about
history today. So we'll not discuss
that.
Vishpala says, "How did the evil
practice of women covering their faces?"
This is the this is the last question
for today. How did this evil practice of
women covering their faces entrenched
become entrenched into Indian society?
Uh even today I see newlywed women
covering their faces. Uh this isn't the
case with southern India. Well, there
there are some clues in that, isn't
isn't it? There are some clues when it
comes to the fact that southern India
doesn't have this issue.
How is it? So
see
the truth is and lots of people get very
upset when I point this out. Look at our
temple carvings from which are older
than 10,000 years which is temple
carvings that were done before the
foreign occupation of India. How are
women depicted in in the temple carvings
of India in the period before the
foreign occupation before the Turk
occupation of India?
You will see women wearing less clothes
and men also
people wore the kind of clothes that
were suitable or appropriate for the
climate of India which is typically for
much of India pretty warm climate. So it
was common for people to wear pretty
what you would call flimsy or sky skimpy
clothes
that's how India was north as well as
south
okay
uh before the Turk occupation even in
Gandhari you will see topless women's
statues
in Gandhara Gandhara is a place where it
snows and yet people used to wear wear
the the clothing so India was very much
like that then what happens is we have
the Turk
invasions and occupation of India, they
came with a very different culture,
they would cover their women and any
woman who was not fully covered was seen
as a piece of flesh
and which is why Indian women had to
start go start hiding indoors and if
they ever came out they had to cover
themselves completely
and that had to become a tradition just
for the for the sake of survival. Our
people had to make it. They had to
transform this into a cultural tradition
that in our our land women and girls
they cover themselves completely. Why?
Simply so that they could live with some
honor. Otherwise they would be abused by
the Turks. So that became a practice for
a thousand years. Why is it not
prevalent prevalent in the south?
Because the south never came under Turk
occupation. Most of it that's the deal.
It is not our culture. I think we should
do away with that today.
Anyway, it's up to people to decide what
they want to live, what kind of
lifestyle to live, who am I to tell
them. But this is the root cause. Even
in Gandhari, you will see statues. I can
show you today if you want. Uh what is
it called? Hunza. Hundz. What is it?
Hunza. Hunza.
Uh Hunza Valley. uh Gandhara art
Buddhist deatas. Let's see. Uh do we
find something?
Um
okay. Buddhist start is generally Gotham
Buddha, right? Uh female.
You are seeing more of more in art.
Okay. I'm I'm I'm not sure where I had
seen this but you will find Gandhara art
which will depict the female form also
in a topless manner and there was
nothing vulgar about it at all. Okay, we
are talking about our ancestors here. So
we're not talking any nonsense here.
Anyway, that's the deal. So that is how
things changed in this country. Okay.
Right. Okay. Do we have any other Okay.
So some of Ramshi Kalam has taken one
more super chat. What is the question?
Raja Graha was Morian Gupta capital
the British distorted it to Patner. No
that's completely not correct. Let me
explain. Raja is today called Rajir
and Patutra is now called Patna.
I'm not sure who distorted Patutra into
Patna. I'm not sure if the British did
that. Maybe it is the people of Magad
who did that. It's up to them, their
choice. Who am I to say a thing? But I
don't think the British changed
partiputra to Patna. And Raj Gria became
Raj Gir. Let me demonstrate it to you.
Let's go to the map and search for
Rajir.
Rajir. Zoom in to Rajgeir. Ancient city
in the blah blah blah. So if you Google
Raj Gir it will tell you it was
originally called Raj Gha.
Let's go to Google.
If you go to Raj Gir the old name was
Raja Graha. All right sir Mr. Wamshi
Khalim
the point is that Raja Griha became
Rajir and Patiputra became Pata.
All right people let us end this live
stream now. Thank you so much for all
the questions. I really appreciate them.
And uh
one second.
Okay, let's take one. This is this is
not a historical question, sir. Come on.
Let's let's do only history today. Okay,
people. I'll I'll I'll look forward to
seeing you tomorrow and uh tomorrow
we're going to talk about geopolitics
and it's going to be a super chat
session. So, I look forward to seeing
you there. Until then, take care. Thank
you so much for all the questions. It's
always fun taking your questions and I
look forward to seeing you all tomorrow.
Thank you. Take care. Keep learning.
Keep asking questions. Keep raising your
standards. See you tomorrow. Bye-bye.